Guide to the Jewish Federation of Greater Houston records, 1939-1990 MS 714
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Jewish Federation of Greater Houston records
1939-2018
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Jewish Federation of Greater Houston; Wunsch, Lee; Actor, Lori K.; Wizig-Barrios, Renee
MS 714
2.25 Linear Feet 3 boxes
This collection which spans 1939 to 2018 includes a 1939-1943 notebook from the Refugee Services Committee which assisted Jews fleeing the Nazi regime in WWII, as well as a variety of photographs of people and events from the Federation's activities in the 1980s. The addendum includes event programs, guides, and one VHS recording.
Biographical / Historical
The origins of the Jewish Federation of Greater Houston date to 1936, when a committee led by Rebecca Nathan was charged by Houston Jewish communal leaders, including Joe Weingarten and Simon Sakowitz, to explore the establishment of an organization that would oversee Jewish philanthropic and social welfare activities in a centralized fashion. The first meeting of the Jewish Community Council was called by Max H. Nathan, Rebecca's husband, in April 1936. Subsequently, in November of that year, Max Nathan was elected the first president of the Council, while M.M. (Mose) Feld became vice-president and Abram Geller served as secretary-treasurer. The Council acquired office space in the West building in downtown Houston, and in 1937, Jacob Lightman, previously with the American Jewish Joint Distribution Committee, was hired as the organization's first Executive Director. In 1977, the Council changed its name to the Jewish Federation of Greater Houston.
The central mission of the organization in its early years was the United Jewish Campaign, an effort to unify the fundraising efforts of the Houston Jewish community and to raise funds for Jewish causes both at home and abroad. The resources of the Council were put to the test during the 1940s, when more than 400 Jewish refugees came to Houston fleeing Nazi persecution. A Refugee Services Committee was organized to assist these men and women with employment, housing, and other needs. The records of this committee are included in the collection.
In the decades since its founding, the Jewish Federation of Greater Houston has been engaged in advocacy on behalf of Israel, Jews in the former Soviet Union, and other international causes. Closer to home, the Federation supports a variety of community initiatives, from philanthropic gifts to Jewish education to senior care.
Notable executive directors who have guided the Federation include Hans Mayer, who served from 1977 to 1996, and Lee Wunsch, who served as President and CEO from 1999 to 2017. As of 2018, the President and CEO of the Federation is Avital Ingber.
Website: https://www.houstonjewish.org/
Scope and Contents
This collection which spans 1939 to 2018 includes a 1939-1943 notebook from the Refugee Services Committee which assisted Jews fleeing the Nazi regime in WWII, as well as a variety of photographs of people and events from the Federation's activities in the 1980s. The addendum includes event programs, guides, and one VHS recording.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Mr. Lee Wunsch, Jewish Federation of Houston, October 2017, and Josh Furman in 2019.
Related Materials
This collection forms part of the Houston Jewish History Archive at Rice University. For related collections, see http://libguides.rice.edu/c.php?g=762169.
Index Terms
Subjects
Jews and Jewish life; Judaism--Customs and practices; Emigration and immigration
Document Types
photographs; notes; newspapers; certificates
Subjects (Persons)
Wunsch, Lee; Actor, Lori K.; Wizig-Barrios, Renee
- Series I: Refugee Services Committee, 1939-1943
  - Refugee Services Committee notebook, 1939-1943 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Handwritten notebook documenting the committee members, meeting minutes, and the activities of different subcommittees, such as the Children's Placement Committee.
- Series II: Photographs of people and events, 1980s
  - Jewish Federation of Greater Houston images, including Jewish Community Center building, events, and people, ca. 1969 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Jewish Federation of Greater Houston images, including United Fund Jewish Community Council building, events, and people, ca. 1969 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Individual photographs, last names A-D (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Names include: Hilda Aron; Lynne Aronoff; Gilbert Baker; Phil Aronson; Stanford Alexander; Golda Baker; Shmuel Ben-Shmuel; Nancy Beren; Marion H. Bernstein; Dr. Daniel Brener; Sharon Brener; Lorraine Brown; Robert A. Caplan; Seymour Cohen; Paul Colbert; Sergiu Commisiona; Leon Davis; Scott Davis; Bill Dinerstein; Ted Dinerstein; Abe "Honey" Donsky; Helen Dow
  - Individual photographs, last names E-G (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Names: Eydie Eisen; Marcia Elefant; Elaine Epstein; Vikki Evans; Harold Falik; Cheryl Falik; Tom Falik; Dr. Bernard Farfel; Theba Feldman; Rabbi Sally Finestone; Dr. Alan Fisherman; Jacqueline Fox; Seth Freedman; Janet Frost; Charlett Frumin; Dr. Marshall Frumin; Mark S. Gardner; Milton Gelman; Gilbert Gertner; Mildred Gertner; Scott Gertner; Shirley Gluckman; Lynn Goldberg; William J. Goldberg; Willy Goldberg; Don Graubart; Noel Graubart; Dr. Steven Greenberg; Mel Gross
  - Individual photographs, last names H-K (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Names include:Carol Hoffman (Miriam Mendell); Stanley Horn; Barbara Horwitz; Joseph Hurwitz; Laura Huvard; Siegmund Izakson; Dr. Arnold Kagan; Lisa Kalmin; Ginger Kaplan; irvin Kaplan; Kathy Kaplan; Linda Kashar; Dr. Morton Katz; Col. Albert Kaufman; Ann Kaufman; Stephen Kaufman; Sol Kirschner; Susan Klaiman; Gail Klein; Suzanne Kornblit; Gary Kornblith; Joe Kornfeld; J. Livingston Kosberg; Saranne Kosberg
  - Individual photographs, last names L (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Names include: Abe Lack; Ruth Lack; Bob Landaver; Sidney Ladin; David I. Lampe; John Landa; gary Landson; David Lerman; Fred Levine; Milton Levit; Diane Levy; Marcia Levy; Nat Levy; Randy Levy; Paul Lynn
  - Jewish Federation events, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    General Assembly Nov. 1987; Super Sunday 1988; United Jewish Campaign 1987-88; Bureau of Jewish Education 1987-88; Community Relations Committee 1987-77; Women's Division 1987-88; Endowment Fund 1987-88
  - "How Your Contribution Helps" photos, including photos from JCC Day Camp of Senior Adults, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Individual and event photos, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Series III: Jewish Herald Voice newspaper issue, 1990
  - Jewish Herald Voice newspaper, June 28, 1990, cover stories on Soviet Jews immigrating to America (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Series IV: Oversize, ca. 1950-2006
  - "Jewel of an Evening" Day proclamation, honoring 40th Anniversary celebration of United Orthodox Synagogues, signed by Mayor Bill White, Feb. 23, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Group photograph including Eddie Cantor, Joe Weingarten, and others, ca. 1950s (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Group photograph of unidentified men near a commercial airplane, ca. 1950s (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Commemorative certificate presented to the Jewish Community of Houston, from the People of Israel, honoring the 25th anniversary of Israel, 1973, signed by Zalman Shazar, Golda Meir, David Ben-Gurion, Louis A. Pincus (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Architectural rendering of home on Chartres and Clay, possibly the original location of Seven Acres Jewish Senior Care, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - United Jewish Campaign - Victory! poster, n.d. (Map-drawer 189, Folder 17)
  - Matted photos of groundbreaking (Map-drawer 189, Folder 17)
- Series V: Addendum, 1996-2018
  - Guide to Jewish Organizations in Houston, 1996-1997 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Shalom Houston - A Guide to Jewish Houston (2), n.d. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Yom Limmud programs (4), 2014-2016; 2018 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - "Collage" program, 2016 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Annual meeting programs (2), 2016-2017 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - "A Renewal of Spirit" [VHS], n.d. (Box 3)